Officially is ס"ט, Samech Tes, we pick up at the top of
ס"א עמוד ב', Samech Alef Amud Beis, and we have introduced the
idea of the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that
an אילונית, ailonis, a woman who is not just unable to have
kids, I mean we haven't really defined the physical characteristics of an
אילונית, ailonis, but a woman who is more like completely out of
the category in some ways in which her body has developed and
so on, it's like childbirth was never part of the equation and
he says that that that that woman would be forbidden to a
כהן kohen because of a it's a she'd be in the category
of זונה. zonah. And coming from a very particular perspective that sex
without the context of procreation, even the bigger larger context of procreation
in some theoretical way, is considered to be an act of זנות.
zenus. And that's going to be very important in terms of ongoing
discussions and is certainly not the only rabbinic attitude towards marital sex.
Then the גמרא Gemara quoted the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says that a כהן kohen cannot marry a minor or קטנה
ktana and it's trying to figure out why. And what's significant is
it does not suggest the idea of זונה zonah there. Like what,
every minor girl is a זונה zonah until she becomes able to
have kids, or even sort of calling it a type of ביאת
זנות bias zenus because again somebody who can in the if that's
in the offing and in large part of the larger context, the
גמרא Gemara does not even suggest that that would be part of
the conversation. So that's not the issue. So what's it about? So
the first suggestion we have is that רבה Rabba said
because combination of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda idea that an אילונית ailonis is forbidden to
a כהן kohen and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who's concerned with minority
opinions, חיישינן למיעוט, chaishinan lemiut, actually not minority opinions, minority likelihoods,
מיעוט, miut, and therefore don't marry a קטנה ktana because she might
grow up to become an אילונית. ailonis. Okay so that's the גמרא's
Gemara רבה's Rabba suggestion, now let's see if the גמרא Gemara challenges
this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכדרבי מאיר
מי סבר לה,
U'k'Rabbi Meir
misavar lah, does he really hold like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So
the line starts with the word סבר לה, savar lah, it's about
fifteen lines down from the top. וכדרבי מאיר מי סבר לה, U'k'Rabbi
Meir misavar lah, does he really hold like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
והתניא, Veha tanyah, but we taught in the ברייתא, Baraisa, קטן וקטנה
לא חולצין ולא מייבמין, koton u'ktana lo choltzin velo meyabmin, דברי רבי
מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that a קטן
koton and a קטנה, ktana, we've it's so funny that it was
anonymous that we've dealt with all these things of יבום yibum and
now we're on a totally different track and we have yet to
deal with this question about whether you have to be an adult
or not when you do יבום. yibum. Thank you. So he says
that a minor, a קטן koton and a קטנה, ktana, minor boy
or girl, cannot do חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum. אמרו לו לרבי
מאיר, Amru lo le'Rabbi Meir, they said to him, אמרו לו לרבי
מאיר, Amru lo le'Rabbi Meir, יפה אמרת שאין חולצין. yafeh amarta she'ain
choltzin. Ya, it's a good it's a good point, yeah they cannot
do חליצה. chalitzah. Why? איש כתיב בפרשה, Ish ksiv b'parsha, because it
says איש, ish, לא יחפוץ האיש, lo yachpotz ha'ish, if the man
doesn't want to. ומקישינן אשה לאיש, Umakishinan isha le'ish,
and since it talks about her and connects her to him, so
therefore the same way the word איש ish is understood to mean
an adult, so he has to be an adult and she has
to be an adult in the act of חליצה. chalitzah. אלא מאי
טעמא אין מייבמין, Ela mai taama ain meyabmin, but why not יבום?
yibum? Because since יבום yibum is not about intent, right, we looked
at the beginning whether מזיד mazed or שוגג, shogeg, even אונס anus
and רצון ratzon and the whole thing, it's just about the simple
act of sex and since we have been seeing that we consider
it halachically to be an act of sex when the girl is
over three years old, and we haven't said it yet but when
the boy is over nine years old, so it's an act of
sex and you don't need כוונה, kavanah, so why can't it work?
לקיים שם המת,
L'kayem
shem ha'mes, right? So קטן koton can't do that.
Yeah, that's
but that doesn't have to be immediately possible either. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אלא מאי טעמא אין מייבמין? Ela mai taama
ain meyabmin? אמר לה, Amar leh, קטן שמא ימצא סריס. koton shema
yimtza saris. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said yeah,
there's no intrinsic reason why they can't, but if it turns out
later that the minor is actually a סריס, saris, right, so also
like not just non-fertile but somehow again סריס saris is a more
about the entire you know a larger physical aspect of him, again
we're not going to unpack that yet now, but
anyway and וקטנה שמא תמצא אילונית, v'ktana shema timtza ailonis, and the
young girl maybe she'll turn out to be an אילונית, ailonis, or
maybe one of them will turn out to be a type of
a person that in a sort of in seen like in a
in terms of their very physical being are out of the category
of having kids, and therefore that's not the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum in those cases. ונמצאו פוגעים בערוה, Venimtzu pogin b'ervah, and then
if that's if that's true there wouldn't have been a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibum and if there was no מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum then it would be an act of, right, forbidden sex, עריות,
arayos, because it would be brother's wife. Okay so that's what he
said. He says technically they could but again not just if it
happens to be, he doesn't say שמא תמצא עקרה, shema timtza akarah,
right, or שמא ימצא עקר, shema yimtza akar, right, so but so
that's important to note it does not necessarily mean that just because
sex isn't possible practically practically impossibly practically. that it's not the מצוה
mitzvah of יבום. yibum. But somehow the person of an אילונית ailonit
and a סריס, saris, and we haven't exactly defined why, are seen
as more categorically excluded, and that's why also the idea of why
before we were saying an אילונית ailonit is a זונה, zona, it's
in a fundamental categorical way. And he says, and therefore that might
happen, and therefore they can't do it now because then retroactively they
will have had, they will have had
forbidden sex because of brother-in-law. Now you could say they would be
minors when they were forbidden sex, but maybe one would have been
an adult and the other would have been a minor. So the
adult would have been really transgressing, right? You understand how, right? So
the adult would have been transgressing in that case even though the
other person wasn't an adult. Also what's interesting is
that it's suggesting is that at the age of בר/בת מצוה Bar/Bat
Mitzvah you'll know the issue of אילונית ailonit or סריס, saris, right?
You won't know yet the question of, what? Which you didn't know
before. Right. So those are things to be thinking about when we
get to more specific descriptions of what אילונית ailonit and סריס saris
is, because the question about whether somebody is fertile or not is
not something you can know at the age of בת מצוה, Bat
Mitzvah, right? And anyway this woman's been married to the brother for
20 years, so maybe there's a good reason to think she's not
fertile, right? So, right? It's not just she's just בת מצוה. Bat
Mitzvah. But nevertheless that's the classic case of יבום. yibum. Okay. So
therefore it's something very specific about אילונית ailonit and סריס saris and
something somehow that can be identified or begin to be identified at
the age of בר/בת מצוה. Bar/Bat Mitzvah. Because it's an ערוה ervah
because there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. And once it's not
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, it's not ערוה ervah because of
an איסור issur to have sex with a סריס. saris. When there's
no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, then it's the איסור issur of
brother-in-law. That's, or sister-in-law. Okay. Did you have a question before? No.
We're assuming that, that a קטן, katan, that a קטן katan can
have sex.
Yes,
I said that. Yeah, that's the same way we've been assuming that
it's considered a halakhic act of sex by a girl even over
three years, by a קטן katan we say even over nine years.
So for example if a, if a married woman has sex with
a boy who's nine years and a day, and she does it
intentionally, so even though he is not punishable yet, you know, for
her it's an act of adultery and it's completely punishable, right? Or
same if it were case of incest or whatever. As long as,
once it's an act of sex because even if one of the
parties is underage, the other party is culpable. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's position, חיישינן
למיעוטא. chayshin le-miuta. ותניא, ve-tanya, okay, fine. וקטנה תניא שבאמת אינה חולצת
דברי רבי אליעזר.
ve-ktana tanya shebe-emet einah
choletzet divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
But look, I'll show you that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't hold
with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that
a קטנה ktana can do יבום, yibum, not חליצה, chalitzah, because she's
categorically excluded. איש כתוב בפרשה מקשינן אשה לאיש. ish katuv ba-parsha makshinan
isha le-ish. Okay, so just in order to do חליצה chalitzah you
have to be an adult, and just that's one of the criteria.
But for יבום yibum he says okay. So he's not concerned with
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So you cannot construct a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer position combining רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
number one. He's not concerned with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. He's clearly
not concerned about the minority possibility. Point number one. And even though
we've already proved our point, we're going to prove that he doesn't
hold with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda either.
So ורבי יהודה מי סבר לה? ve-Rabbi Yehuda mi savar leh? You
really think he'll hold like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: זונה, zona, זונה כשמה. zona kishmah. And
now we have a nice little list of positions in the תנאים
Tannaim about, it's so fascinating, without almost any גמרא Gemara exploring what
is the biblical category of זונה zona for a כהן. Kohen. So
the first one says זונה כשמה, zona kishmah, literally a זונה, zona,
which is not very helpful. What do you mean a זונה? zona?
זונה zona is what it says, it's a זונה. zona. דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. Now
you and I might think that means okay, a prostitute, a woman
who's standing on the street corner prostituting herself. But then רבי עקיבא
אומר זונה זו מופקרת. Rabbi Akiva omer zona zu mufkeret. No, זונה
zona is a woman that is like, you know, הפקר, hefker, like
doesn't,
indiscriminately having sex with people. So maybe it's different, maybe it's not
she's not selling sex, but she's still completely, what's the word? Not
licentious, licentious? Promiscuous, right.
So, now רש"י Rashi says on זונה כשמה, zona kishmah,
where's רש"י? Rashi? כשמה, kishmah, if you look at רש"י Rashi about
eight lines down in the narrow lines, לשון טועה שטועה מתחת בעלה
לאחרים, lashon to'eh she-to'eh mitachat ba'alah la-acherim, דלרבי אליעזר אין זונה אלא
אשת איש. de-le-Rabbi Eliezer ein zona ela eshet ish. Okay, which is
very interesting. I certainly wouldn't have thought that's what it means זונה
כשמה, zona kishmah, but he says זונה zona is a woman who
committed adultery. That's the way רש"י Rashi is reading זונה כשמה. zona
kishmah. So
right, exactly. But I'm saying it's funny that not, you know, the
statement זונה כשמה zona kishmah doesn't help so much. So רש"י's Rashi's
explaining it in a very different way than I might have explained
it. רבי מתיא בן חרש אומר אפילו הלך בעלה להשקותה ובא עליה
בדרך עשאה זונה.
Rabbi Matya ben Charash
omer afilu halach ba'alah le-hashkotah u-va'ah aleha ba-derech asah zona. Any act
of forbidden sex, even an act of forbidden sex that occurs within
the context of marriage, she is suspected of having committed adultery, so
there's this איסור issur that even her husband can't have sex until
it's cleared up, and it's only an איסור issur because of a
doubt. It's not like a fundamental status of her as a person.
Right. And nevertheless even transgressing
Now there's another sort of minor איסור *issur*, minor whatever, it's a
prohibition, but it's in the context of marriage, and nevertheless a woman
is still forbidden to her husband, and that would be מחזיר גרושתו
*Machzir Grushato*, right? His wife whatever it's just מחזיר גרושתו *Machzir Grushato*,
right? But that we can't use as an example because that woman
is already a גרושה *Grusha*. It's not an interesting case for a
כהן Kohen *Kohen*, okay? So this is a case that is completely
within the context of a completely legitimate marriage, and nevertheless it's a
forbidden act of sex that makes her a זונה zona. *Zonah*. רבי
יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, Rabbi Yehuda says זונה zonah זו אילונית
*Zonah zu ilonis*, which is what we saw in the משנה mishnah
*Mishnah*. וחכמים אומרים אין זונה zonah אלא גיורת משוחררת שנבעלה בעילת זנות
zenus *V'chachamim omrim ein Zonah ela giyores meshuchreres shenivala beilas zenut*. So
the בעילת זנות *beilas zenut* is number one more limiting than רב
מתיא בן חרש *Rav Masa ben Charash* because that would only be
an איסור כרת *issur kares*. An איסור כרת *issur kares* or an
איסור כהונה *issur kehuna*, okay, that although if it's an איסור כהונה
*issur kehuna* she's already out from that perspective, so maybe not an
איסור *issur*, let's bracket that, that might be more about a חללה
*chalala*. But anyway, that's for the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim*, okay? Whereas, we
discussed that yesterday, or we discussed it at the beginning of today,
and what do you mean we exactly discussed it? And גיורת ומשוחררת
*Giyores u'meshuchreres* is, as we said, either concerns about having had sex
with a non-Jew or a fundamental assumption of how to look at
the non-Jewish world. And that's the חכמים *Chachamim*, okay? So so far
though that's all very nice, but we're not up to רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar? *Rabbi Elazar*, which is the one that we're trying to
figure out whether רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* holds like רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* or not in terms of this of an אילונית
*ilonis*. So now we say like this: רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer. *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, Rabbi Eliezer says, now there's a question whether
before it was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer* or רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar *Rabbi Elazar*. Before we're saying רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi
Eliezer* was the one who said זונה zonah כשמה *Zonah kishmah*, and
here it's רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar, אומר *Rabbi Elazar omer*, Rabbi Elazar
says: פנוי הבא על פנויה שלא לשם אישות עשאה זונה *panai haba
al penuyah she'lo leshem ishus asah Zonah*. Any act of extramarital sex,
okay? Not any act of forbidden sex, but he's even more extreme
than רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* who says promiscuous. He says doesn't matter
promiscuous, you could have a committed relationship but it's extramarital sex, that
makes her a זונה *Zonah*. And anyway, for our purposes, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, who's the one we're trying to nail down
about why he says that a כהן Kohen *Kohen* can't marry a
קטנה Ktana? *Ktana*, he says it's זונה כשמה *Zonah kishmah*, which זונה
כשמה *Zonah kishmah* you could either take to mean literally a prostitute
or you could mean a woman who's committed an act of adultery
like רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, but it certainly is not אילונית *ilonis*, okay?
Now so we're still trying to now understand so why does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* say a כהן Kohen *Kohen* can't marry
a קטנה Ktana. *Ktana*? Now before we get to the next answer,
again, I just want to reiterate here you have such a like
a whole wide range of different opinions of what is this category
of זונה *Zonah* in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, you know, with no
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* analysis on it and it has very fraught imp
so strong implications for כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*, you know, nowadays, exactly that
and particularly the whole issue of גיורת *Giyoras* as we mentioned. I
do want to mention one thing about פנוי הבא על פנויה *panai
haba al penuyah*, if you take a look at the little תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos*, right, non-marital sex or extramarital sex, the little תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos* פנוי הבא על פנויה *panai haba al penuyah* also says: לאו
דוקא נקט פנוי דכל שכן נשואה *lav davka nakat panai d'kol sheken
nesuyah*, it's not just that they both are single, okay? It means
even if they're both single, but it would certainly be a problem
if he's married, why? שמזנה על אשתו דחשובה זונה *Shemezanneh al ishto
dechashuva Zonah*, because if he's married then it's even worse then he's
cheating on his wife, okay? So if they say even if they're
both single and unattached, and even if it's not הפקר *Hefker*, it's
committed relationship, it's still זונה *Zonah*. So what I found fascinating about
this תוספות *Tosfos* is that it sort of is very much of
what we sort of express as a modern sensibility about the idea
of adultery, right? It's either partner, you know, right? But הלכתית *halachically*,
right, the marriage only limits the woman, it doesn't limit the man,
right? And there with a polygamous הלכה halacha *halacha*, not if the
society was changing, at least הלכה halacha. *halacha* allowed for polygamy. So
what do you mean cheating on your wife if you're having sex
with another woman? I mean, you know, just read what we're reading
about יעקב *Yaakov* and all his four wives and so on. So
it doesn't I think it's fascinating that he says yeah, there's even
more זנות *znus* because you're cheating on your wife, which maybe reflects
the reality in אשכנז *Ashkenaz*, you know, and רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu Gershom*
and the whole thing about the norms of a monogamous relationship that
he's calling that being מזנה על אשתו *mezanneh al ishto*, so I
thought that that was quite significant. Okay, yes?
See because to me when I see זונה *Zonah*, like it doesn't
it sounds more like a desc like a person like that as
opposed to a descriptive one act kind of thing. Right, okay, yeah,
so that's sort of like where I'm running
I agree, so that in a way אילונית *ilonis* is even better
because that's totally about the person. So you're saying maybe you don't
understand how a single act of forbidden sex, yeah, I understand that,
but the problem is saying well it's the person who generally, I
don't know, like sells her body, where exactly when does that status
start, when does it end, how many times does she have to
have done it or whatever? That's why, you know, if you say
one particular concrete act does it, it's much more quantifiable. Okay, and
now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues says like this, so we're still
trying to figure out why a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* can't marry a
קטנה Ktana *Ktana* according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אלא אמר רבא Ela amar Rava, בר
אבא הכא hacha, בכהן גדול עסקינן b'Kohen Gadol askinan. *ela amar Rava
bar Abba hacha b'kohen gadol askinan*, oh, talking about a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol*. Now remember... Now remember, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol.
also according to many can't marry a בוגרת. bogeret. So הכא, right,
why רבי אליעזר says a כהן Kohen. can't marry a קטנה? Ktana
בכהן גדול עסקינן. So ואימת קני לה? v'eimata kani la? So now
let so now he can't marry a בוגרת bogeret and he also
can't marry a קטנה. Ktana? Why? Because when is he going to
acquire her? And meaning he's assuming that she's married
off not by the father, she's married off by let's say herself.
You have a קטנה Ktana. emancipated or whatever, she goes ahead and
she marries herself to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol Oh, well then
they're having sex, he's having sex with her, right, before there's real
קידושין. Kiddushin. So ואימת קני לה? v'eimata kani la? When will he
acquire her? When will there be קידושין? Kiddushin? לכי גדלה, l'chi gadla,
when she becomes adult. At that stage, בעולה be'ula היא. hi. She's
already a woman that is—that is a non- a non-virgin. So אמר
amar רבא Rava מכלי לב. machli lev. Rava said that was like—that
was an un- a non-thought of like, Rava says it means מבלי
לב. mi'blei lev. Like you said it without—you said that without thinking.
He says we can't be talking about that. אי דקידשה אבוה, i
d'kidshei avu'a, what's the case? If the father married her off, מההיא
שעתא הוא דקני לה, me'hahi sha'ta hu d'kani la, then they're married
and obviously then it's totally fine. ואי דקידשה נפשה, v'i d'kidshei nafsha,
she married herself off, הא רבי אליעזר, ha Rabbi Eliezer, what it's
only רבי אליעזר? ולא רבנן? v'lo rabanan? Of course everybody would agree
that if they're not married and they're having sex and then they
get married, she's a בעולה. be'ula. Now of course it would have
been interesting to explore the case about what if the mother and
brothers marry her off, right? What would, you know—but okay, but that
presumably would be the same. I mean it might make it ביאת
זנות, bi'at znut, we talked before about having the rabbinic קידושין Kiddushin
redefine whether it's ביאת זנות bi'at znut or not, but it would
still make her בעולה be'ula when it's time to get married halachically.
So the גמרא Gemara, says רבא Rava says that would not be
a unique position of רבי אליעזר. אלא אמר amar רבא, לעולם בכהן
הדיוט. le'olam b'Kohen Hedyot. We're going back to a כהן הדיוט. Kohen
Hedyot. וחיישינן שמא תתפתה עליו. v'chaishinan shema titpateh alav. And what we're
concerned about is don't marry her because maybe she will be seduced
and therefore by another man and therefore she will be a—she'll be
an אשת איש eshet ish and a זונה. Okay, so אי הכי
i hachi says the גמרא, Gemara ישראל נמי. Yisrael nami.
Yeah, so then
no, even a non-כהן Kohen shouldn't marry a קטנה Ktana. because we're
assuming that underage will be more easily seduced. So he says no,
פיתוי קטנה אונס הוא, pittuy ktana ones hu, which is our—which is
the very reasonable position, right, which we have you know in secular
law as well which is—which is called statutory rape. Okay. Now of
course we have statutory rape if the girl is like sixteen or
something. Certainly when the girl is under twelve, statutory rape makes a
complete amount of sense. Say there was no what degree of רצון
ratzon can we really be talking about there? And obviously we would
see that as abuse and as rape. So that's what he says.
So therefore ואונס בישראל מישרא שרי. v'ones b'Yisrael meishra shari.
So if she's married to a non-כהן Kohen and somebody manages to
seduce her and have sex with her then she'd be מותרת muteret
to her husband because it's considered אונס, ones, right? And it's considered—it's
considered non-volitional. But if she's married to a כהן, Kohen it doesn't
matter whether it's volitional or not and she'll be forbidden to her
husband. So that's one answer. רב פפא אמר בכהן גדול. Rav Pappa
amar b'Kohen Gadol. Back to כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, והאי תנא הוא
דתניא. v'hai tana hu d'tanya.
It's the following תנא tana who teaches: בתולה. betula. יחול קטנה? yachol
ktana? Maybe he'll marry a קטנה? Ktana, תלמוד לומר אשה. Talmud lomar
isha. It says והוא אשה בבתוליה. v'hu isha b'vituleha. אי אשה, i
isha,
if she's an adult woman, יחול בוגרת, yachol bogeret, maybe fully mature?
תלמוד לומר בתולה. Talmud lomar betula. And for him בתולה betula often
means a, you know, a נערה, na'ara, נערה בתולה. na'ara betula. So
בתולה betula means or complete בתולים, betulim, not בוגרת. bogeret. So but
somehow for him it also means—I'm not exactly clear but somehow it
also means not a קטנה. Ktana So I'm sorry אשה isha means
not a קטנה. Ktana So אשה isha means not a קטנה, Ktana
but בתולה betula means that the hymen is completely in its, you
know, unchanged. So what's that spot in the middle between being a
woman and the hymen being unchanged? הכיצד? Ha'keitzad? יצאה מכלל קטנה ולכלל
בגרות לא באת. yatz'a m'klal ktana u'l'klal bagrut lo ba'at. And therefore
it's a נערה. na'ara. So according to this a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, can only marry a woman between twelve and twelve and a
half—a girl.
Right. Different answer. Different answer.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar האי
תנא הוא. hai tana hu. So that's—so now we've got one answer
that we're going by is we're afraid she'll be seduced and it'll
particularly be a problem married to a כהן. Kohen Second answer we're
going by is because that the only woman a כהן Kohen can
marry, until now we've been saying a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol we're
talking only about a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol and until now we've
been saying בוגרת bogeret is a problem, now we're saying the word
אשה isha makes a קטנה problem and the only person he can
marry is a girl between twelve and twelve and a half. The
following answer רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר האי תנא הוא דתניא. Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak amar hai tana hu d'tanya. The following תנא tana
where we taught: בתולה, betula, אין בתולה אלא נערה. ein betula ela
na'ara. בתולה betula is only a
נערה. na'ara. וכן הוא אומר v'chen hu omer והנערה טובת מראה מאד
בתולה ואיש לא ידעה. v'ha'na'ara tovat mareh m'od betula v'ish lo yeda'ah.
So of course you might say if it has to say בתולה
betula it means that נערה na'ara doesn't communicate that, but nevertheless he's
saying that those are normally seen as in—as indicating the same status.
Okay, same idea though. A כהן גדול has to marry only a
נערה. na'ara. רבי אליעזר אומר. Now last, okay, so that's the position
of רבי אליעזר that כהן can't marry a קטנה or כהן גדול
can't marry a קטנה for whatever reason. Back to the—ending up this
סוגיא. sugya. רב אלעזר... Rav Elazar... That a woman is a זונה
for a כהן if she's had extramarital sex even if they're both
single. אמר רב עמרם אין הלכה כרבי אליעזר. Amar Rav Amram ein
halacha k’Rabbi Eliezer. We don’t rule like that position. Now is it
רבי אליעזר or רבי אלעזר? רבי אלעזר seems to be, right? אין
הלכה כרבי אלעזר ein halacha k’Rabbi Elazar like the position we just
quoted, excuse me, I missaid it. And therefore that’s very important, you
know, because as I said, nowadays a כהן is getting, you know,
when כהנים have are getting married, if the woman has had sex
with a non-Jew, it’s a real issue, you know, it’s a very
serious problem and those those things come up not infrequently. But according
to רבי אלעזר, if she’s had if she’s ever had sex with
anyone, you know, non-marital context, then you know then it would then
she’d be אסורה לכהן, asura l’Kohen, so we do not פוסקן pasken
that way.
What about an איילונית ayalonis אסורה לכהן? asura l’Kohen?
I don’t know. Okay, I don’t know, because we פוסקן pasken like
the חכמים that a זונה is only this category. Okay. Now, now
because we mentioned the issue about marrying an איילונית, ayalonis, a כהן
marrying an איילונית ayalonis and whether איילונית ayalonis is in the זונה
category, and also that introduced us to the idea whether non-marital about
about sex, marital sex in the non-procreative context is considered to be
זנות or not, and specifically we’re dealing with the whole issue of
פרו ורבו, pru urvu, which is now a perfect segue into this
משנה Mishnah to discuss פרו ורבו. pru urvu. So the primary place
in the גמרא Gemara that discusses the מצווה mitzvah פרו ורבו pru
urvu is not in קידושין Kiddushin and not in כתובות, Kesuvos, but
in יבמות. Yevamos. Okay. So which is interesting, you know, it’s interesting,
if you think about it, קידושין Kiddushin is more about the act
of קידושין kiddushin itself, right, the you know the act of the
giving of the ring or whatever, it wasn’t a ring in time
of the גמרא, Gemara but anyway. כתובות Kesuvos is more about the
state of נישואין, nisuin, right, the second stage, the חופה, chuppah, the
act of חופה chuppah and the being married and the reciprocal obligations
and so on. And יבמות, Yevamos, in addition to being about ייבום,
yibbum, is a lot about personal status and also things relating to
sex, right? We had all the whole discussion about what constitutes an
act of sex etc., and therefore in also related way we’re getting
to the topic of the מצווה mitzvah פרו ורבו. pru urvu. Okay,
although this easily could have been in כתובות. Kesuvos. So let’s take
a look.
לא יבטל אדם מפרו ורבו, lo yevatel adam mi’pru urvu, a person,
a
man should not stop from having
children unless he has children, which is a very funny way of
framing it. Why don’t we say like when are you יוצא yotzei
the מצווה mitzvah פרו ורבו? pru urvu? But maybe it means because
פרו ורבו pru urvu it’s not like taking a לולב lulav and
an אתרוג, esrog, right? I mean some people are trying for a
very long time. So it could be saying don’t stop trying, you
know, oh we’ve tried for a long time we’re not having kids.
Oh you don’t stop trying or you don’t start making efforts to
have it happen like or let’s say a person’s married to a
woman for twenty years his wife dies, right, which is like a
classic ייבום yibbum case. Don’t sort of, you know, you still have
the מצווה mitzvah פרו ורבו. pru urvu. So you know so it’s
a frame dealing with the phase don’t stop until as opposed to
you’re יוצא yotzei when. Okay, so you still you’re obligation of פרו
ורבו pru urvu is incumbent until you have children. Now how many
children? בית שמאי אומרים שני זכרים, Beis Shammai omrim shney zecharim, two
males, ובית הלל אומרים זכר ונקבה, u’Beis Hillel omrim zachar u’nekeivah, male
and female, שנאמר זכר ונקבה בראם, shene’emar zachar u’nekeivah bera’am, male and
female he created them, so which indicates that the purpose of פרו
ורבו pru urvu for בית הלל Beis Hillel is what? You know,
why זכר ונקבה בראם? zachar u’nekeivah bera’am? That’s not in the מצווה
mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru urvu. I mean sort of פרו ורבו
pru urvu is somewhere in those פסוקים pesukim nearby but it’s not
exactly in the מצווה mitzvah פרו ורבו. pru urvu. So what’s that
indicating for בית הלל Beis Hillel that the purpose what’s the purpose
of פרו
ורבו? pru urvu?
What? Why would anyway say somebody say the מצווה mitzvah of פרו
ורבו pru urvu is a boy and a girl?
In order
to continue populating the world. Now you could just say everybody should
have two kids and the law of averages it’ll all work out,
right, which is true, right? So if you think about it communally,
what as opposed
to not really, because of what’s happening in China, right, everybody could
only have
naturally, naturally.
If you naturally have kids and two kids and you don’t manipulate,
what
he’s doing perhaps is that maybe in a male-dominated society or where
male children are preferred, it’s necessary to
underscore that you have to have a girl. And we’ll get to
that in terms of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Okay, but right, but
so A, it’s to continue to populate the world, but also by
quoting זכר ונקבה בראם, zachar u’nekeivah bera’am, you could go a little
bit further. Exactly, it’s like imitatio dei, like competing like you know
being like God, not just achieving the goal that there are enough
men and women in the world and the world continues to be
populated, but you know and achieving the ציווי tzivuy of פרו ורבו
ומלאו את הארץ pru urvu u’mil’u es ha’aretz to continue to have
the world filled and populated but also to be sort of replicating
that original divine act of creation and creating male and female. So
that makes a lot of sense according to בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
What do the בית שמאי Beis Shammai say? Two men, right? Certainly
it’s not about continuing the act of populating the world, that doesn’t
happen if everybody stops at two men, although I tried to do
the averages I’m sure Charlie could do this, this would be a
fun assignment. If every if people keep on having kids and everybody
stops once they have two boys, what will be the distribution of
boys to girls? Okay, it’s a fun math puzzle but it’s not
as totally skewed as you would imagine, right, because sometimes you start
with two boys, sometimes two girls, a boy and a girl. Anyway,
but it still would be a skewed population.
So obviously בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. We'll take
a look.
Maybe you could say that it's like replicating yourself and if it's
the מצוה mitzvah on the man and it's פרו ורבו peru u'revu
it has to be a זכר zachar from there.
Maybe. I don't see how you get two.
פרו. pru. פרו. pru. מרבו. merbu.
מרבו. merbu. Okay, that's interesting. That's interesting.
Yes, and with modern child mortality rates, I think the accepted numbers
for repopulation is 2.1 for children. It is. It's here 2.1.
Why? Oh, because of the cases of stress and illness and infertile
and whatever, right?
Because people die before
they're...
Aha. Aha. Right.
2.1. Because if everybody has exactly 2.0 children, then you have a
declining population.
Ah, but even according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you're not always
having 2.0. You're trying to בית הלל Beit Hillel is clearly it's
going to be more than two because many people will start off
with two boys or two girls.
No, 50% of people will stop at two when you have boy-girl
or girl-boy. The other 50% who have two boys or two girls
will have to have three. So the actual average will be at
least, I have to do the math, but at least something like
either 2.5 or 2.25. I think 2.5 or something. Right, Charlie, is
that right?
I'm sorry, I was looking it up.
If everybody stops at a boy and a girl, right?
Or stops at two boys, either way they're going to have more
because then what if they have two girls and then they have
to keep going, right?
Right, but they have to keep going according to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. So with either opinion you're going to have more than
an average of two.
I know, that's what I'm saying. That's what I'm saying. But you
actually have according to בית הלל Beit Hillel you probably have 2.5,
right?
I'm looking it up right now.
Okay. No, okay, I think it's a binomial. Fine. Okay. So anyway,
fascinating questions. But I think that's a good point that I never
stopped to think about, which is not just division of the population
but what exactly would be the birth rate that would come out
of that? But no, even according to בית הלל Beit Hillel you're
having clearly like a 2.25 or 2.5 birth rate. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: היש לו בנים, hayesh lo banim,
so if somebody has kids, מפירו ורבו בטל, m'peru u'revu batel, if
the implication is then you can stop worrying about having more kids.
By the way, that's also important because it doesn't just say stop.
Like is there a מצוה mitzvah to have is two a minimum?
Is there a מצוה mitzvah to have more than two? A קיום
מצוה? kiyum mitzvah? A bigger מצוה? mitzvah? Obviously you have very large
families nowadays, particularly in, you know, חרדי Haredi communities and so on.
Is that part of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו? peru u'revu?
So that's another important question that we have to ask about the
nature of the obligation beyond the minimum. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying that the משנה Mishnah sounds like don't stop until you're יוצא.
yotzei. Once you're יוצא, yotzei, you can stop. But מאישה לא בטל.
m'isha lo batel. Stop having kids, but you can't, as talking to
the man, not worry about being married. מסייע ליה, mesayeia lei, that's
the way it's inferred. מסייע ליה לרב נחמן אמר שמואל, mesayeia lei
l'Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, this supports רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel, אמר רב אדא amar Rav Ada who says: אף על
פי שיש לו לאדם כמה בנים, af al pi sheyesh lo l'adam
kama banim, even though a man already has a couple of kids,
אסור לעמוד בלא אישה. assur la'amod belo isha. His wife died or
they got divorced, no, he has an obligation to be married, that's
separate from procreation. Important, right? Before we were talking about sex only
in the context of procreation. This isn't sex, this is marriage. And
nevertheless he says, even once the מצוה פרו ורבו mitzvah peru u'revu,
is no longer relevant, there's an intrinsic value of being married. שנאמר,
shene'emar, as the verse says: לא טוב היות האדם לבדו. lo tov
heyot ha'adam levado. It is not good to be alone. There's an
intrinsic value of human beings, you know, you know,
being in marriage, being connected to another person and the state of
marriage is an intrinsic good. It's important to note that because another
way it's framed elsewhere is, you know why it's important for a
man to be married even if he's already had kids? Because otherwise
what will happen?
It's probably good for him to be in a sexual relationship and
not to transgress.
Right,
otherwise you'll have problems about זרע לבטלה zera levatala or sexual transgression.
You know, so there's a way of saying you should be married
to make it very instrumental and not an intrinsic good. So this
is a very important גמרא Gemara, that it sort of says beyond
kids, marriage is an intrinsic good. Yes.
Although if you look at history, men have not been very good
in general as
even when they are married? Okay, that's a separate conversation, but hopefully
better when they are married. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So again, very important גמרא Gemara in terms of thinking about
the, you know, sex in a procreative context, marriage in a procreative
context or a non-procreative context. Okay.
Why not quote the, I don't remember the phrase, but that a
woman prefers to be married. Right. But here it's applied to anybody,
right?
Here it's about responsibility not preferred. The גמרא, Gemara טב למיתן. tav
lemetan. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says like this: איכא דאמרי ika d'amri
others say, היש לו בנים, hayesh lo banim, we want to read
the משנה Mishnah. the following: if you have kids, בטל מפירו ורבו.
batel m'peru u'revu. No, that's not the implication of the משנה. Mishnah
The משנה Mishnah. only once you have kids, you can forget about
the whole thing. בטל מפירו ורבו batel m'peru u'revu ובטל נמי מאישה
u'batel nami m'isha and maybe you don't have to worry about being
married. Sounds like just okay, then you're done. Okay, fascinating how you
could read opposite things out of the משנה. Mishnah So נימא תהוי
תיובתא דרב נחמן אמר שמואל, neima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav Nachman amar Shmuel,
maybe that's a contradiction to רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Rav Nachman amar
Shmuel, because רב נחמן אמר שמואל Rav Nachman amar Shmuel says because
I let me sort of explain what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
It's not just a textual דיוק. diyuk. How do you stop having
kids in a society which has no effective forms of birth control?
Right? How do
you stop having
A because of human nature in the context if they're already married,
A because of human nature and B because it's a central obligation
of marriage. So the only relevance would be if the man is
no longer married, his wife has died or divorced, and it's discussing
whether he needs to remarry or not, right? So the question of
whether you still have to be trying to have kids in a
society where there's no birth control, what's the conversation? Why don't you
just say the conversation is, you know, if I'm married and I'm
having sex with my wife, of course we're still trying to have
kids. So the only relevance of that conversation is when he's not
married, whether he has to remarry. Okay, whether he has to get
married again. So therefore the first way of reading it is, okay,
you don't have to get married again in order to worry about
kids, but you still have to get married again. And the other
way of reading it: No, if it's telling you I don't have
to worry about having kids anymore, and right now I'm not married,
what it's telling me is I don't have to get remarried. Yes.
There were contraceptives back in Talmudic times, although we've lost them today.
And second, coitus interruptus significantly reduced the fertility rate in France in
the 19th century.
Okay, but there's a whole question about that and whether that's הלכה
halacha or non-הלכה. Okay, fine, but that's a good point. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לימא תהוי תיובתא Neima tehevei tiyuvta so if
you're saying no kids, it's implicitly saying no wife? So this let's
see, is this a contradiction of רב נחמן אמר שמואל? Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel? לא, Lo, no, it's not a contradiction. אין לו בנים
נושא אשה בת בנים. Ein lo banim nosei isha bat banim. No,
no, no, because what it's saying is there's still a way to
be married and not have kids, which is, how old is your
wife? Or, right? So if you are, if you don't have kids,
then when you're getting married you have to marry a fertile woman.
יש לו בנים, Yesh lo banim, if you do have kids, maybe
you still have to get married, but when I'm telling you you
don't have to get kids, what I'm telling you is, נושא אשה
דלאו בת בנים nosei isha de-lav bat banim that you can choose
to marry a woman who's not fertile. Okay, so I'm not telling
you you don't have to get married, but you don't have to
marry a woman that is fertile, that's what it's saying.
Okay, and נפקא מינה, nafkaminah, תוספות says like why do you need
another נפקא מינה, nafkaminah, you just gave me a נפקא מינה, nafkaminah,
but the נפקא מינה nafkaminah is also למכור ספר תורה בשביל בנים
limkor sefer torah bishvil banim that we're going to see later that
the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו peru u'revu is so great that
you would even sell a ספר תורה Sefer Torah in order to
allow you to get the funds to try to get married and
so on. And that would only be in the context before you're
יוצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah But after you're יוצא yotzei the מצוה,
mitzvah. when it says בטל מפריה ורביה, battel mipru u'revu, what it
means is that you don't have to go ahead and like sell
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you don't have... or you're not
allowed to do that in order to be מקיים mekayem the מצוה
mitzvah, once you're already מקיים mekayem it, but it does not mean
that you do not have to be married. There's a value of
being married regardless. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says the משנה Mishnah
is vague about מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו, peru u'revu it's vague about
the intrinsic value of marriage, and it's reading the משנה Mishnah to
reaffirm either way that it's definitely important to be married regardless of
the מצוה mitzvah of having kids. And the only question is about
like whether you have to make sure that you're able to have
kids or not, or what type of allowances do we give to
enable the marriage, you know, even in terms of selling a ספר
תורה. Sefer Torah. That's the only relevance. All right, now moving on.
בית שמאי אומרים שני זכר. Beit Shammai omrim shnei zachar. Now we
get to the definition of פרו ורבו. peru u'revu. So בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says two males. So מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? mai ta'ama
deBeit Shammai? Good question. What we were asking: What's the reason of
בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? So ילפינן ממשה. yalfina miMoshe. We learn from
משה. Moshe. דכתיב בני משה גרשום ואליעזר, dikhitiv benei Moshe Gershom ve-Eliezer,
which is not a מאי טעמא mai ta'ama of the type of
question we would ask. It's sort of like where, you know, what's
their biblical source? Where do they get defining it that way? Oh,
'cause משה Moshe had two kids. Of course who said משה Moshe
was יוצא פרו ורבו? yotzei peru u'revu? Well, presumably, you know, he
went to stop with two boys, not two kids, two boys, had
he not been יוצא. yotzei. Okay, but that is not... and why
did he stop? All right, but that is not telling us the
logic behind it. ובית הלל ילפינן מברייתו של עולם. UBeit Hillel yalfina
mibiryaso shel olam. בית הלל Beit Hillel as we see in the
משנה learns out from how God created the world. So ובית שמאי
ליליף מברייתו של עולם? uBeit Shammai lifol mibiryaso shel olam? Why doesn't
בית שמאי Beit Shammai learn from that? Which is again fascinating, like,
that's not in the context of the מצוה, mitzvah, but nevertheless, it's
a very powerful argument in itself about how God created the world
and the idea of procreating the world. So the גמרא Gemara says:
No, אין דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. ein danin miefshar mishe'i efshar. So
it's not just how God created the world, what's clear now that
the גמרא Gemara understands is it's also about how אדם וחוה Adam
ve-Chava had kids. God said to אדם וחוה, Adam ve-Chava, פרו ורבו
ומלאו את הארץ. peru u'revu u'milu et ha'aretz. How... what type of
kids did they have to have? All boy, all girls? No, they
had to have boys and girls. So the first fulfillment of פרו
ורבו peru u'revu had to be boys and girls. So בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says, yeah, that's not relevant 'cause the world wouldn't have
gotten started without that. But now, we don't have to worry about
the entire world and society and about there being enough boys and
enough girls in the world, that'll sort of take care of itself
and that's not our responsibility, and therefore it does not have to
be a boy and a girl. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says:
ובית הלל נמי ליליף ממשה? uBeit Hillel nami lifol miMoshe? So why
doesn't בית הלל Beit Hillel learn from משה? Moshe? אמר לך, amar
lakh, משה מדעתיה הוא דעבד. Moshe mida'atei hu de'avid. No, you know,
that was משה's Moshe own decision, it was really not the... it
was really not a model that anybody else could follow. and he
maybe wasn't being מקיים פרו ורבו, m'kayem pru u'rvu, והסכימה דעתו לדעת
המקום, ve'hiskima da'ato l'da'at ha'makom, and his intent was in line with
God's desire. פירש מן האשה דקתני Perash min ha'isha de'katani because we
taught שלשה דברים עשה משה מדעתו והסכימה דעתו לדעת המקום Shelosha devarim
asa Moshe m'da'ato ve'hiskima da'ato l'da'at ha'makom three things Moshe sort of
decided on his own and it turned out that he was that
was what God wanted. פירש מן האשה Perash min ha'isha he separated
from his wife after Mount Sinai, ושיבר הלוחות ve'shiber ha'luchot he broke
the לוחות, luchos, והוסיף יום אחד ve'hosif yom echad and he added
one day to the period leading up to Mount Sinai. פירש מן
האשה מאי דריש Perash min ha'isha mai darish where did he get
the idea to separate from his wife after Mount Sinai? אמר אמר
ומה ישראל שלא דיבר עמהם שכינה אלא שעה אחת Amar amar u'mah
Yisrael she'lo diber imahem shechina ela sha'ah achat when God spoke to
the Jewish people even for one moment, וקבע להם זמן ve'kava lahem
zman and told them only at this time from you know the
from the time the shofar blasts and then it'll be over when
the shofar isn't blasting, אמרה תורה אל תקרבו אל אשה amra Torah
al tikrevu el isha they weren't allowed to have sex leading up
to it, אני שמייחד עמי דיבור בכל שעה ושעה Ani she'meyached imi
dibur be'chol sha'ah ve'sha'ah I that God can speak to me at
any time, I don't know when God's going to speak to me,
ולא קבע לי זמן ve'lo kava li zman and I don't know
ahead of time when it's going to happen, על אחת כמה וכמה
al achat kama ve'kama how much more so do I have to
constantly be ready to that union with God and therefore I cannot
be with my wife and I cannot have a sexual relationship with
my wife, I always have to be in a state of being
prepared to you know have the communion with God.
So now how do we know והסכימה דעתו לדעת המקום ve'hiskima da'ato
l'da'at ha'makom how do we know God agreed to this? שנאמר shene'emar
because it says לך אמור להם שובו לכם לאהליכם lech emor lahem
shuvu lachem l'oholeichem go tell them go back to your tents, tents
meaning be with your wives, again speaking to the men, ואתה פה
עמוד עמדי ve'ata poh amod imadi but you stay here with me
which is being read as not just for the time being but
in a regular state of being, in an existential way you're always
going to be standing with me and ready to commune with me
and therefore not back in your tent.
שיבר הלוחות מאי דריש shiber ha'luchot mai darish where do you see
he broke the לוחות, luchos, you know where do you see that
he sort of you know how do we where are we going
to explore again you know what Moshe's thoughts were, we're not linking
it to a פסוק pasuk but we're sort of speculating or assuming
what must Moshe have been thinking that he thought it was the
right decision to break the לוחות. luchos. So אמר he said the
following, ומה פסח שהוא אחד משש מאות ושלש עשרה מצות u'mah pesach
she'hu echad mi'shesh me'ot u'shlosh esreh mitzvot Pesach which is just one
of 613, אמרה תורה כל בן נכר לא יאכל בו amra Torah
kol ben nechar lo yochal bo the Torah says that a foreigner
cannot eat from it, but a foreigner is defined halachically as somebody
who שנתנכרו מעשיו לאביו שבשמים she'nitnachru ma'asav l'aviv she'ba'shamayim somebody who has
distanced himself from God, somebody who has violated the Torah, not just
a single violation but somebody who has become like rejected the Torah.
So where were
we, התורה כולה ha'Torah kula so if it's the entire Torah and
ישראל מומרים ve'Yisrael mumarim so if so if the Jewish people are
a מומר, mumar, so על אחת כמה וכמה al achat kama ve'kama
how much more so should they not be able to receive the
Torah, to receive it. Of course that's pretty funny you could say
no you may be a מומר mumar you exclude from one thing,
you don't exclude from everything, but he sort of said no if
somebody is a מומר mumar and they're excluded from the פסח pesach
how much more so should they not be able to be accept
the entire Torah and accept the לוחות. luchos. Okay, והסכימה דעתו לדעת
המקום ve'hiskima da'ato l'da'at ha'makom
and that was exactly what God had intended, דכתיב אשר שיברת de'chtiv
asher shibarta that the you know the לוחות luchos that you broke.
ואמר ריש לקיש ve'amar Reish Lakish and so here's a classic rabbinic
wordplay אשר שיברת asher shibarta
read it the following way יישר כחך אשר שיברת. yishar kochacha asher
shibarta.
So אשר asher is like you know שכח, shkoyach, שכח shkoyach like
they even sometimes you know שכח shkoyach ששיברת. she'shibarta. Alright so it's
pretty what? The whole Torah was on the לוחות luchos that it's
not not classic.
Right,
that's also true or somehow embedded in it, it's a good point
too you know the whole idea that you can categorize all 613
מצות mitzvot under the עשרת הדברות aseret ha'dibrot is a very but
it goes all the way back to like Philo, it's a very
early idea, but you're right in some ways it's implicit here seeing
it you know it could just be seen as like being representative
of the 613 but maybe it's even suggesting somehow embedded in it
as are the 613,
one of the one of the opinions right? That what was on
the לוחות luchos was the whole Torah. The whole Torah, yeah.
So the גמרא Gemara, goes like this, okay. הוסיף יום אחד מדעתו
hosif yom echad mida'ato how about one day before Mount Sinai? Notice
that all these three are in the context of Mount Sinai for
what that's worth. Okay he added one day of separation leading up,
דכתיב וקדשתם היום ומחר de'chtiv ve'kidashtam hayom u'machar prepare them today and
tomorrow. היום כמחר hayom kemachar so that's only two days. But Moshe
said one minute today has to be like tomorrow, now today already
started. So אמר מחר לילו עמו amar machar leilo imo so the
same way tomorrow is a full day starting from the night before,
אף היום לילו עמו af hayom leilo imo so to get two
days it has to be two complete days starting from the night
before, והאי לילא דידי נפקא ליה ve'hai leila deidi nafka leh
but today we're already past the last night, שמע מינה תרי יומי
לבר
מהאידנא shma mina trei yomei l'bar me'ha'idna it must be two full
days starting after today. והסכימה דעתו לדעת המקום ve'hiskima da'ato l'da'at ha'makom
and that was correspondent to God's intent. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, so anyway all of that was a...
yeah, by the way, take a look quick look at תוספות התורה
כולה וישראל מומרים. Tosafot ha-Torah kulla ve-Yisrael mumarim. תוספות says אין זה
קל וחומר גמור דשאני פסח משום דקדשים אבל כל התורה כולה הלא
ויש
ללמדם
ולהחזירם
בתשובה.
ein zeh kal va-chomer gamur de-shani pesach mishum de-kodshim
aval kol ha-Torah kulla hala ve-yesh
le-lamdam u-le-hachziram bi-teshuva. Right, so it's a very bizarre קל וחומר kal
va-chomer of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, one מצוה mitzvah to
exclude
you
from,
but it's a very big difference. Okay, anyway fine.
Now, but now the so anyway that's the point, you can't learn
from משה. Moshe. משה Moshe is a special case. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara goes on. By the way, there are some ראשונים Rishonim
that think that ask, would בית הלל Beit Hillel agree to בית
שמאי? Beit Shammai? When בית הלל Beit Hillel says a boy and
a girl, would בית הלל Beit Hillel say, but you could also
be יוצא yotzei with two boys? So this גמרא, Gemara it's not
פשט pshat at all because we learn from בריאתו של עולם וצורתה
beri'ato shel olam ve-tzuratah and this whole point about משה Moshe also
indicates it because they're basically saying you can't learn from משה, Moshe,
which is basically to say according to me משה Moshe wasn't יוצא
פרו ורבו, yotzei pru u-revu, but he's an exception. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, תניא, Tanya, tell me the ברייתא. Baraita.
רבי נתן אומר בית שמאי אומרים שני זכרים ושתי נקבות.
Rabbi Natan omer Beit Shammai omrim
shenei zecharim u-shtei nekevot.
Now we have a different version of it, talk about a high
birth rate. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you need two boys
and two girls. So he basically agrees to the idea of boy
and girl as procreation as the
key, but maybe the idea of פרו ורבו, pru u-revu, you know,
פרו pru gets a boy and a girl, רבו revu is doubled.
Okay, בית הלל אומרים זכר ונקבה, Beit Hillel omrim zachar u-nekeva,
what we always knew, but a completely different version of בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. אמר רבינא מאי טעמא דרבי נתן אליבא דבית שמאי? Amar
Ravina mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Natan aliba de-Beit Shammai? דכתיב ותוסף ללדת את
אחיו את הבל. de-chtiv va-tosef laledet et achiv et Hevel.
So she continued to give birth his brother, קין's Kayin brother, הבל.
Hevel. So הבל ואחותו. Hevel ve-achoto.
So את et is understood to be like like with a sister
because there's no girls that are described. Obviously there must have been
girls but they're not described. So it means הבל Hevel and his
brother... I'm sorry, ואת אחיו את הבל, ve-et achiv et Hevel, so
הבל ואחותו, Hevel ve-achoto, קין ואחותו. Kayin ve-achoto. So since it was
she did the same with הבל Hevel as she did with קין,
Kayin, so we're going to assume הבל Hevel had a sister and
קין Kayin had a sister. וכתיב, u-chtiv, and then it says because
when she has שת, Shet, כי שת לי אלהים זרע אחר תחת
הבל כי הרגו קין. ki shat li Elohim zera acher tachat Hevel
ki harago Kayin. Okay, so God has given me another one because
under הבל Hevel because קין Kayin killed him. And why is that
relevant? So if you take a look at רש"י Rashi near the
הגהות הב"ח, hagahot HaBach, ומה דהגהות הב"ח: u-mah de-hagahot HaBach: כי שתי
זרע אחר תחת הבל אמר
תשלומין בא
ki shati zera acher tachat
Hevel amar
tashlumin ba ולא סגי בלא שני זכרים ושתי נקבות. ve-lo sagi be-lo
shenei zecharim u-shtei nekevot. Right? It sounded like we have to replace
him.
Now maybe she just wants to replace him because you know she
wanted as a human being as a human being, but no, it's
understood the reason she
had
שת Shet was because now that הבל Hevel is dead she wasn't
מקיים mekayem the מצוה mitzvah anymore. So she needed to have another
קין. Kayin. And somehow we're assuming it also means with a girl.
Alright, so that's how the גמרא Gemara is sort of reading that,
reading that out of that story. The thing that I would say
also relevant is the question which the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask. If somebody has a boy and a girl and God forbid
one of his children are you know die, does he have to,
was he already יוצא, yotzei, or does he have to or does
he have to like leave behind a boy and a girl? Right?
So that's so here it's sounding like she wasn't יוצא yotzei anymore.
So now she had to do this to be יוצא. yotzei.
Okay, ורבנן ve-rabbanan and the Rabbis say no, הודיה דקא מודה.
hoda'aya de-ka moda. She's just thanking God for giving her a new
child. It's not like, oh now I was יוצא. yotzei. Okay, תניא
אידך, tanya idach, we find another ברייתא. Baraita. רבי נתן אומר בית
שמאי אומרים זכר ונקבה. Rabbi Natan omer Beit Shammai omrim zachar u-nekeva.
Now we have another different version. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says male
and female, what has for us been
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. בית הלל אומרים או זכר או נקבה. Beit
Hillel omrim o zachar o nekeva. So one child, talk about a
low birth rate. אמר רבא מאי טעמא דרבי נתן אליבא דבית הלל?
Amar Rava mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Natan aliba de-Beit Hillel? So בית שמאי
Beit Shammai we don't have to explain, but what's this idea of
בית הלל Beit Hillel one child? שנאמר לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה.
she-ne'emar lo tohu vera'ah la-shevet yetzarah. So this is a פסוק pasuk
that is used in the context of פרו ורבו pru u-revu to
talk about the purpose of פרו ורבו. pru u-revu. And what's fascinating
by the way about a lot of the הלכתי halakhic issues around
פרו ורבו pru u-revu is normally we don't we tend to think
about more technical questions. Ah, the פסוק pasuk says איש ואשה ish
ve-isha whatever, you know, or an איש ish עושה חליצה, osei chalitza,
קטן katan לא עושה חליצה. lo osei chalitza. By פרו ורבו, pru
u-revu, it's much more on the surface what's the point of this
מצוה. mitzvah. And when we figure out what the point of the
מצוה mitzvah is, that's going to guide a lot of the הלכתי
halakhic parameters, which is a pretty reasonable approach, except that very often
in הלכתי halakhic derivation, it's that's not on the surface and it's
usually more technical issues. So here what the גמרא's Gemara saying is
and the use of the פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו Yeshayahu that God
did not create the world to be desolate but to be settled
is very much used in the context of understanding the purpose of
פרו ורבו. pru u-revu. So okay, but you would say that should
be a boy and a girl.
No, והוי ליה שבת, ve-havei lei shevet, if you even settled the
world so settling the world, right is you know maybe having another
child and having somebody that's going to continue to contribute to the
world, but it's not necessarily repopulating the world or continuing to, you
know, which is so fascinating because if you ask me which פסוק
pasuk more describes the purpose of פרו ורבו, pru urvu, לא תהו
בראה לשבת יצרה, lo tohu bera'ah lashaivet yetzara, which emphasizes לשבת, lashaivet,
to settle the world, or פרו ורבו, pru urvu, what are the
next words? ומלאו את הארץ, umilu et ha'aretz, right? So מלאו את
הארץ milu et ha'aretz is much more, you need to continue to
procreate and you know to continue that. That would much more point
to the boy and the girl, so it's interesting that this is
now taking precedence. Okay, אתמר itmar was taught. היו לו בנים בהיותם
עובדי כוכבים ונתגייר, Hayu lo banim biyotam ovday kochavim venitgayer, somebody had
children when they were non-Jew and then he converted. So how much
is a person fulfill the מצוה, mitzvah, a) because he has children
even if he didn't sort of have them when he was Jewish,
and then it also gets to that whole biological question about that
הלכה doesn't you know sort of in those cases does not see
them as sort of being part of this person's family legally being
the person's children, but they are biologically the person's children. By the
way, that whole idea you know what I think is often hard
for us to get our head around: how can they you know
say they're not his kids? You know think about what happened in
in like you know in in earlier in other societies about the
whole idea of bastard children, right? Bastard children was a biological child
but was not legally recognized as the person's child. Okay, so here
by the question somebody who converted and had biological children, they're not
legally recognized as his children but they are his biological children. Is
that relevant for פרו ורבו? pru urvu? But he also also didn't
have them when he was Jewish. Are you is there a מצוה
mitzvah פרו ורבו pru urvu on non-Jews? If you're יוצא yotzei as
a non-Jew, are you יוצא yotzei as a Jew? Okay, so let's
take a look. היו לו בנים בהיותם עובדי כוכבים ונתגיירו, Hayu lo
banim biyotam ovday kochavim venitgayru, רבי יוחנן אמר קיים פרו ורבו. Rabbi
Yochanan amar kiyam pru urvu. You're מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו. pru urvu.
ריש לקיש אמר לא קיים פרו
ורבו. Reish Lakish amar lo kiyam pru urvu. You're not. רבי יוחנן
אמר קיים פרו ורבו Rabbi Yochanan amar kiyam pru urvu דהוו ליה.
dihavay lay. He has children, which both means a) biologically there are
enough and that's okay, and b) even though the actual having of
them was when he was not Jewish, now he still has them.
Oh, okay, or you could read it he was יוצא yotzei as
a non-Jew, but it could also be that now he still has
them. ריש לקיש אמר לא קיים פרו ורבו, Reish Lakish amar lo
kiyam pru urvu, גר שנתגייר כקטן שנולד
דמי. ger shenitgayer k'katan shenolad dami. They're not considered his kids anymore,
and therefore it's not relevant. Okay, ואזלו לטעמייהו, ve'ozlu lita'amayhu,
and they go according to their reasonings. דאתמר, de'itmar, היו לו בנים
בהיותם עובדי כוכבים ונתגיירו, hayu lo banim biyotam ovday kochavim venitgayru, רבי
יוחנן אמר אין לו בכור לנחלה. Rabbi Yochanan amar ein lo bechor
lenachala. Okay, somebody had a biological kid as a non-Jew, and now
he's converted and has a his first child as a Jew. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says he doesn't have a status of בכור,
bechor, because he's not a biological first child. Okay, דהוה ליה ראשית
אונו. dihavay lay reishit ono. The first of his strength he had
biologically. ריש לקיש אמר יש לו בכור לנחלה, Reish Lakish amar yesh
lo bechor lenachala, גר שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי. ger shenitgayer k'katan shenolad
dami. No, it's like completely new, starting from a clean slate, and
this is considered his first child. וצריכא, utzricha, you need to have
the debate in both cases. דאי אשמעינן בהא קמייתא, di'ashmiyinan behay kama'itay,
if it was just the question of the מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו,
pru urvu, בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן משום דמעיקרא נמי בני פרו ורבו
נינהו. behay ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum demayikara nami b'nay pru urvu ninhu.
It's one thing to say you're מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו pru urvu
as a non-Jew because then it was in the category of פרו
ורבו pru urvu even as a non-Jew. Now what does that mean?
You could just say okay biologically you could have kids even as
a non-Jew, but what it also suggests is not just the biological
reality, it suggests that non-Jews maybe have a מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו.
pru urvu. That's not such a big חידוש. chiddush. For God's sake,
God says it first to אדם Adam and חוה, Chava, then God
says it to נח, Noach, right? He sort of says it to
all of humanity, so to say that the מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו
pru urvu is for all of humanity is not a big חידוש.
chiddush. However, there are other גמרות Gemaras that suggest not, and there's
actually a fascinating מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim whether non-Jews have a מצוה
mitzvah פרו ורבו. pru urvu. Let me ask you a question: is
it a מצוה mitzvah to set up two non-Jews, you know, to
make a שידוך shidduch between two non-Jews? So פרו ורבו, pru urvu,
מלאו את הארץ, milu et ha'aretz, right? Or is it and thinking
about the point of פרו ורבו pru urvu is very different if
you think about it as a מצוה mitzvah on the Jewish people
or you think about it as a מצוה mitzvah on the entire
world. So this גמרא Gemara very much suggests, which shouldn't be a
חידוש, chiddush, it's פשט pshat of the entire of the תורה, okay,
I mean not just פשט pshat like a technical reading, it's the
whole point, it's a universal command that there's they're מצווה metzuveh even
as non-Jews, although it's not listed like in the שבע מצוות בני
נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach and so on, so that's why it's
the there's a lot of debate around that. So that's why he
says, he says, okay, it would be one thing to say you're
מקיים mekayem it as a non-Jew because it's not only they're biologically
your kids but you were in the פרשה parsha of the מצוה
mitzvah פרו ורבו pru urvu then also, so it should be יוצא
yotzei now that you've converted. אבל ענין נחלה דלאו בני נחלה נינהו,
aval inyan nachala d'lav bnei nachala ninhu, but by inheritance where they're
not in the category of inheritance. Now, of course, non-Jews have laws
of inheritance too, but it means that they're not in like the
הלכתי halachic categories of inheritance. So דראוי לנחלה הוא, de'ra'ui lenachala hu,
ורמי נינהו, v'ramay ninhu, אימא מודי ליה לריש לקיש, ayma modeh lay
l'Reish Lakish,
maybe he'd agree to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you start fresh
when you convert. דאתמר בהא, de'itmar beha, if you just did the
case of inheritance, בהא קאמר ריש לקיש. beha ka'amar Reish Lakish. That's
where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says you start fresh because it's a
completely new category of halachic inheritance, אבל בהאי, aval b'hai, but the
case of פרו, pru, אימא מודי לרבי יוחנן, eima modei l'Rabbi Yochanan,
maybe he admits to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan because that's more about
biologically having kids and maybe non-Jews are in the מצוה mitzvah of
having kids, so maybe he would concede it. צריכא, tsricha, so you
have to tell, so you see that it's a debate, you have
to say that they argue both cases. Okay, רש"י Rashi says בני
נח, Bnei Noach, בני פרו ורבו נינהו, bnei pru u'rvu ninhu, דכתיב,
d'chtiv, ויאמר להם פרו ורבו. vayomer lahem pru u'rvu. Sorry, I had
it right here at the פסוק, pasuk, of course, God, you know,
told אדם Adam and חוה, Chava, כלל, klal, all of creation has
a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. Okay, אתייה רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש. atayei Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. Now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
asks ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, בעת היא שלח בראדך בלאדן בן בלאדן
מלך בבל וגו'. ba'eis hi shalach Bradoch Baladon ben Baladon melech Bavel
etc.
So at that time, you know, בראדך בלאדן Bradoch Baladon the son
of בלאדן, Baladon, the king of בבל Bavel sent, sent etc. So
what do you see? So you see that, that they recognize a
sense of who your father is. So you see non-Jews have a
sense of who their father is. Just a bizarre proof, isn't it?
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said, he said to them, בעודן עובדי
כוכבים, b'odan ovdei kochavim, אית להו חייס. is l'hu chayus. I'm admitting
that as non-Jews you're considered not only a biological father but a
legal father, but נתגיירו, nisgaiyru, לית להו חייס, leis l'hu chayus, once
they convert, that relationship is no longer legally recognized. Okay, אמר רב,
amar Rav, or אמר רב אמי, amar Rav Ami, הכל מודים בעבד
שאין לו חייס. hakol modin b'eved she'ein lo chayus.
Everybody admits that with a slave who was then freed, had kids
as a slave and was then freed, that there is no, there
was no even recognized legal relationship even initially. So therefore there could
be no מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. דכתיב, d'chtiv, שבו
לכם פה עם החמור, shvu lachem po im hachamor, עם החמור, im
hachamor, the same as עם הדומה לחמור, am ha'domeh l'chamor, with those
that are similar to donkeys, which is not being said here about
all non-Jews but is being said about slaves, understanding that one of
the people he took with, one of them was his עבד, eved,
his slave. Okay, so therefore and of course as we know, certainly
happened in not all slave societies, right? Some slave societies they allowed
people to live as families, is that true? And in others like
in the South, right, they were not allowed to live as families,
right?
But certainly they actually had conditional marriages
until such time that they were breaking up.
Interesting. Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא says as a legal point,
it was you know, no sense of parentage was recognized, you know,
with slaves and therefore everybody would agree there that if a slave
was freed, what happened with his biological kids, he would not fulfill
פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. מתיב, meiseiv, I'll ask you, ולציבא חמשה עשר
בנים ועשרים עבדים, u'l'Tziva chamisha asar banim v'esrim avadim,
ציבא Tziva had fifteen children and twenty slaves. Why do I care
that he had twenty slaves? So,
so presumably it means that his twenty slaves were born from, right,
and רש"י Rashi says, I'm sorry, that wasn't the point. רש"י Rashi
says ציבא עבד כנעני של מפיבושת הוה, Tziva eved Kena'ani shel Mephiboshet
hava, so ציבא Tziva himself was a slave. Okay, and it says
he had fifteen children. So אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, amar Rav
Acha bar Yaakov, כפר בן בקר. k'par ben bakar.
No, it's only describing it biologically, right, like you know you say
that
this cattle had a calf. Okay, so when it says he had
fifteen children, it doesn't mean they were his legal children, it's just
saying he biologically had fifteen children. אי הכי, ei hachi, הכא
נמי. hacha nami.
So if that's true,
one minute, let me just see the
רש"י here about בראדך בלאדן, Bradoch Baladon, right. So in any case,
why do you ever assume that something indicates a sense of legal
parentage? Why don't we just say it all just means biological? No,
שאני התם דיחסינו בשמיה ובשמא דאבוהון, shani hasam d'yachsinnu b'shmayeih u'v'shma d'avuon,
והכא לא מפרש. v'hacha lo mefaresh. No, there it says so-and-so is
the son of so-and-so, which meant that it's legally recognized. So for
non-Jews, parentage is legally recognized. Okay? The only question is what happens
when they convert. But for slaves, it's just biological children; there's no
legal recognition of them as children. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'is eima if you
want I could say, יחסינו בדוכתא אחריתא באבוהון ובאבא דאבוהון. yachsinnu b'duchta
achrita b'avuon u'v'aba d'avuon.
It's even more than that because we see that they get
sort of identified not only with the father but also the grandfather,
so it's not just talking about your biological offspring, there's a sense
of parentage and family. דכתיב, d'chtiv, וישלח מלך אשור בן הדד בן
טברימון בן חזיון מלך ארם היושב בדמשק
לאמר וגו'. vayishlach Melech Ashur Ben Hadad ben Tavrimon ben Hezyon Melech
Aram hayoshev b'Damasek lemor etc. Okay, so by non-Jews as non-Jews, there's
a legally recognized sense of father and child and so on, but
by slaves, it's just biological. The question is when a non-Jew converts,
is the fact that he had the kids and that it was
legally recognized as his kids as a non-Jew and was מקיים m'kayem
the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru u'rvu as a non-Jew, does
that then mean that he continues to be מקיים m'kayem it now
that he has converted? Okay, איתמר, itmar, it was said, I'm going
to just read a little bit more, היו לו בנים ומתו hayu
lo banim u'meisu because this is the other half to the discussion.
It goes back to the חוה Chava case and it goes back
to it might be saying I still have kids I should be
יוצא, yotzei, but that suggests being יוצא yotzei is not having the
kids born, but having them, like on a non—as a state of
having them. Whereas the flip side of that question, in a funny
way, the flip side of the question of having had kids and
then converting, now as a Jew, I still have my biological kids,
even though I didn't birth them—or a man ever births them—even though
I didn't, whatever, anyway I wasn't part of their birthing, you know,
as a Jew, the flip side of that question
is what if, God forbid, the kids predecease the person? So he
had them, but they did not sort of continue to live. Are
you—is he מקיים m'kayem פרו ורבו pru u'revu like the גמרא spoke
in terms of the case of חוה Chava and הבל? Hevel? So
let's take a look, let's just read this very briefly. היו לו
בנים ומתו. hayu lo banim umesu. רב הונא אמר מקיים פרו ורבו.
Rav Huna amar m'kayem pru u'revu. מקיים m'kayem because you had the
kids. ורבי יוחנן אמר לא קיים, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kiyem, you're
not מקיים. m'kayem. רב הונא אמר מקיים משום דרבי אסי, Rav Huna
amar m'kayem mishum d'Rabbi Assi, דאמר רבי אסי, d'amar Rabbi Assi, and
now we get to a question again of what is the מצוה
mitzvah פרו ורבו pru u'revu about? How could you be מקיים m'kayem
פרו ורבו pru u'revu if you didn't leave your replacements behind? No,
because פרו ורבו pru u'revu is about something else, not just about
populating the world. Here's what it's about, רבי אסי. Rabbi Assi. דאמר
רבי אסי אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל הנשמות שבגוף, d'amar
Rabbi Assi ein ben David ba ad she-yichlu kol ha-neshamos she-ba-guf, שנאמר
כי רוח מלפני
יעטוף. she-ne'emar ki ruach mi-lefanai ya'atof. בן דוד, ben David, משיח Mashiach
won't come until all of the souls are used up. Now, גוף
guf here doesn't mean in the body, but גוף guf is understood
as like this storage facility up in heaven. There are all these
souls, unique souls, and they get distributed every time a baby is
born, and when that storage warehouse is empty, that's when משיח Mashiach
is going to come. So the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru
u'revu is to bring about משיח, Mashiach, to start getting those souls
used up. So therefore, even חס ושלום chas v'shalom if the kid
dies, you still מקיים m'kayem the—one of the goals at least of
פרו ורבו. pru u'revu. Okay, so a very fascinating new understanding of
what פרו ורבו pru u'revu is. ורבי יוחנן אמר לא קיים פרו
ורבו, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kiyem pru u'revu, you're not מקיים. m'kayem.
לשבת יצרה בעינן והא ליכא. la-sheves yatzrah ba'inan v'ha leika. It's not
just about having them born, it's about settling the world, and settling
the world means that they are around to settle the world. Okay.
Now again, it's a fascinating question. What would the גמרא think
if somebody had kids and—let's just say that לא קיים lo kiyem
פרו ורבו pru u'revu if they die? So he had kids, he's
now ninety years old, and his seventy-year-old son dies. Is he not
קיים kiyem פרו ורבו? pru u'revu? Like if it's לשבת, la-sheves, does
it mean that he has to predecease them, or does it mean
that they have to have lived an adult life? Like at what
stage are you done? Right, you know the joke, right? This couple,
ninety years old, they come to the judge for a divorce, and
the guy says, "I don't understand, you've been married seventy years, happy
marriage, all of a sudden now you're ninety years old, you come
for a divorce, why now?" He says, "Your Honor, we were waiting
for the kids to die."
So anyway, alright,
so we will continue with that tomorrow, but it is again fascinating
in terms of thinking about how the idea of the goals of
פרו ורבו pru u'revu might shape the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו
pru u'revu and its parameters. And I want to just end by
saying one very important idea, that when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
you're not מקיים m'kayem פרו ורבו pru u'revu if you just have
the kids but it's also
about reaching a certain age of adulthood and maturity and so on,
that leads at a conceptual way of saying that part of the
מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru u'revu is not just having the
kids but raising the kids. And that is also extremely important in
terms of thinking
with couples that are being challenged with infertility, about like is adoption
a way of being מקיים m'kayem פרו ורבו? pru u'revu? And there
are definitely some פוסקים poskim that say that it's at least a
partial קיום kiyum because part of פרו ורבו pru u'revu is not
just the having of the kids but the raising of the kids.
So a lot to think about. Okay, see you all on Sunday.